<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   Documentation for the PERMUT package
-->

<!DOCTYPE Book SYSTEM "gapdoc.dtd">

<Book Name="PERMUT">
<TitlePage>
  <Title><Package>PERMUT</Package></Title>
  <Subtitle>A &GAP;4 package to deal with permutability</Subtitle>
  <Version>Version 2.0.3</Version>
  <Author>Adolfo Ballester-Bolinches
  <Email>Adolfo.Ballester@uv.es</Email>
  <Address>Departament de Matemàtiques, Universitat de València</Address></Author>
  <Author>Enric Cosme-Llópez
  <Homepage>https://www.uv.es/coslloen/</Homepage>
  <Email>Enric.Cosme@uv.es</Email>
  <Address>Departament de Matemàtiques, Universitat de València</Address></Author>
  <Author>Ramón Esteban-Romero
  <Email>Ramon.Esteban@uv.es</Email><Homepage>https://www.uv.es/estebanr/</Homepage><Address>Departament
  de Matemàtiques, Universitat de València. Permanent: Institut Universitari de Matemàtica Pura i Aplicada, Universitat Politècnica de València</Address></Author>
</TitlePage>

<TableOfContents/>

<Body>

<Chapter><Heading>Introduction to the <Package>PERMUT</Package> Package</Heading>
<E>All functions defined in this package deal only with finite
groups.</E> Moreover, some of the
functions assume that the orders of all subgroups are easily computable
and that the decomposition of the order of a group as a product of
prime numbers can be done in a reasonable time.
<P/>

The package <Package>PERMUT</Package> contains some functions to deal with
permutability in finite groups. It includes functions to test some
subgroup embedding properties related to permutability, like
permutability or Sylow permutability. It also
includes some functions to check whether a group belongs to the
classes of T-groups, PT-groups,
and PST-groups, which are the classes of groups in which normality,
permutability, and Sylow permutability, respectively, are
transitive. These properties and classes of groups have been
widely studied during the last years. Most of them are described in
<Cite Key="BallesterEstebanAsaad10" />.
<P/>

The algorithms for T-groups, PT-groups, and PST-groups of this package
use some interesting local descriptions of groups in these classes, that is,
given in terms of some information related to the primes <M>p</M> dividing their
order, usually by looking at <M>p</M>-subgroups or <M>p</M>-chief factors. These
characterisations show that the only difference between
all three classes of groups in the soluble universe corresponds to the Sylow
structure.

Nevertheless, for the sake of completeness, we also provide functions
that use directly the definition of these classes. In the case of
T-groups and PST-groups, as well as for soluble PT-groups, we reduce
the test to subnormal subgroups of defect&nbsp;<M>2</M> (see
<Cite Key="BallesterEstebanRagland07" />, <Cite Key="BallesterEstebanRagland09" />,
and <Cite Key="BallesterBeidlemanCosseyEstebanRaglandSchmidt09" />). Of
course, to do this we must introduce some functions to
check whether two subgroups permute and whether a subgroup is permutable or
S-permutable.
<P/>

Some of the definitions of group-related concepts
appear more than 
once in this manual, in the description of different functions. Although these
repetitions may seem unnecessary when reading the whole manual, we hope that they benefit users who read the online help in &GAP;.
<P/>

In order to obtain easily counterexamples which show that a group or a
subgroup does not satisfy a certain property, we have introduced what
we have called <Q>One</Q> functions, which store such counterexamples. In
some cases, the property can be checked by proving that these
counterexamples do not exist.
<P/>


This package requires the <Package>Format</Package> package by B. Eick and
C. R. B. Wright (see <Cite Key="EickWright03-FORMAT" />), because it uses the
functions <Ref Oper="PResidual" BookName="format"/> and <Ref Oper="SystemNormalizer" BookName="format"/>, which are defined
there.
Some of the examples in this manual use the library of groups of small order.
<P/>

The mathematical foundations of the algorithms presented in this
package have been described in <Cite Key="BallesterCosmeEsteban13-cejm" />.
<P/>

The authors acknowledge the support of the grants MTM2010-19938-C03-01
and MTM2014-54707-C3-1-P
from the <E>Ministerio de Economía y Competitividad</E>, Spanish
Government (all authors), the grant PROMETEO/2017/057
from the <E>Generalitat</E>, Valencian Goverment
(A. Ballester-Bolinches and R. Esteban-Romero), the grant 11271085 from National Natural
Science Foundation of China (A. Ballester-Bolinches) and the
predoctoral grant AP2010-2764 from the <E>Ministerio de Educación</E>,
Spanish Government (E. Cosme-Llópez). The authors are also indebted to the
members of the &GAP; council, especially Leonard Soicher, Alice
Niemeyer, Max Horn, and Alexander Konovalov, as well as to the anonymous referees, for their comments
which have helped us to improve the package and its documentation.
<P/>


</Chapter>















<Chapter><Heading>Installation and Help of the <Package>PERMUT</Package> Package</Heading>

Since all functions of this package are written in the &GAP; language,
it is enough to unpack the archive file in a directory in the <F>pkg</F>
hierarchy of your &GAP; 4 distribution. It has been tested on version 4.7.4 of
&GAP;.
<P/>


The <Package>PERMUT</Package> package requires that the package <Package>Format</Package>
<Cite Key="EickWright03-FORMAT" /> be installed on the system, because it uses
the functions <Ref Oper="PResidual" BookName="format"/> and <Ref Oper="SystemNormalizer" BookName="format"/> which are
defined there. The <Package>Format</Package> package can be downloaded from the &GAP; web page
(<URL>https://www.gap-system.org</URL>).
<P/>

The <Package>PERMUT</Package> package can be loaded with
<Log>
gap> LoadPackage("permut");
─────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
Loading  FORMAT 1.3 (Formations of Finite Soluble Groups)
by Bettina Eick (http://www.icm.tu-bs.de/~beick) and
   Charles R.B. Wright (http://www.uoregon.edu/~wright).
Homepage: http://www.uoregon.edu/~wright/RESEARCH/format/
─────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
─────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
Loading  permut 2.0.3 (PERMUT: A package to deal with permutability in finite groups)
by Adolfo Ballester-Bolinches (Adolfo.Ballester@uv.es),
   Enric Cosme-Ll\'opez (https://www.uv.es/coslloen), and
   Ram\'on Esteban-Romero (https://www.uv.es/estebanr).
Homepage: https://gap-packages.github.io/permut/
─────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
true
</Log>
<P/>

Suggestions, comments, and bug reports can be sent to the email
address <Email>Ramon.Esteban@uv.es</Email>.


</Chapter>
<Chapter><Heading>Permutability of Subgroups in Finite Groups</Heading>
This chapter describes functions to check permutability of
subgroups in a given group. First we present a function to check
whether a subgroup permutes with another one, then we present
functions to test whether a subgroup permutes with the members of a given family of subgroups, and finally we introduce
some other subgroup embedding properties related to permutability.
<P/>

<Section Label="permut-functions"><Heading>Permutability functions</Heading>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="ArePermutableSubgroups" Arg="[G, ]U, V" Comm="with three arguments" />
<Description>
This function returns <K>true</K> if <A>U</A> and <A>V</A> permute in <A>G</A>. The
groups <A>U</A> and <A>V</A> must be subgroups of <A>G</A>. The
subgroups <M>U</M> and <M>V</M> <E>permute</E> when <M>UV = VU</M>. This is equivalent to
affirming that <M>UV</M> is a subgroup of&nbsp;<M>G</M>.
<P/>

This is done by checking that the order of <M>\langle U, V \rangle</M> is
the order of their Frobenius product <M>UV</M>, that is, <M>|U||V|/|U \cap
V|</M>. Hence the performance of this function depends strongly on the
existence of good 
algorithms to compute the intersection of two subgroups and, of
course, the order of a subgroup. Shorthands are provided for
the cases in which
one of <A>U</A> and <A>V</A> is a subgroup of the other one or <A>U</A> or <A>V</A> are
permutable in a common supergroup.
<P/>

In the version with two arguments, <A>U</A> and <A>V</A> must have a common
parent or <Code>ClosureGroup( U, V )</Code> (see <Ref Func="ClosureGroup" BookName="Ref" />) is called to construct a common
supergroup for <A>U</A> and <A>V</A>.

<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);
Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> a:=Subgroup(g,[(1,2)(3,4)]);
Group([ (1,2)(3,4) ])
gap> b:=Subgroup(g,[(1,2,3)]);
Group([ (1,2,3) ])
gap> c:=Subgroup(g,[(1,2)]);
Group([ (1,2) ])
gap> ArePermutableSubgroups(g,a,b);
false
gap> ArePermutableSubgroups(g,a,c);
true
gap> ArePermutableSubgroups(g,b,c);
true
gap> ArePermutableSubgroups(b,c);
true
gap> ArePermutableSubgroups(b,a);
false
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>


</Section>
<Section Label="permut-embedding-properties"><Heading>Embedding properties related to permutability</Heading>

In the following we describe some functions which allow us to test
whether a subgroup permutes with the members of some families of
subgroups. We pay special attention to the families of all subgroups and all Sylow
subgroups of the group. In some cases, we have introduced some <Q>One</Q>
functions, which give an element or a subgroup in the relevant family of subgroups
of the group which shows that the given property fails, or
<K>fail</K> otherwise.
<P/>
<ManSection>
<Var Name="PermutMaxTries" Comm="bound for the number of probabilistic tests" />
<Description>
This variable contains the maximum number of random attempts of permutability checks before trying general deterministic methods in the functions <Ref Oper="IsPermutable" /> and <Ref Func="IsIwasawaSylow" />. Its default value is <M>10</M>.
</Description>
</ManSection>
<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsPermutable" Arg="G, H" Comm="test for permutability" />
<Prop Name="IsPermutableInParent" Arg="H" Comm="test for permutability" />

<Description>
This property returns <K>true</K> if the subgroup <A>H</A> is permutable in
<A>G</A>, otherwise it returns <K>false</K>. We say that a subgroup
<M>H</M> of a group <M>G</M> is <E>permutable</E> in <M>G</M> if <M>H</M>
permutes with all subgroups of&nbsp;<M>G</M>.
<P/>

If the attribute <Ref Attr="OneSubgroupNotPermutingWithInParent" /> has been
set, it is used if possible. Otherwise, the algorithm checks looks for a cyclic subgroup not permuting with <A>H</A>. The number of such cyclic subgroups is controlled by the variable <Ref Var="PermutMaxTries" />, by default, <M>10</M>. If <A>H</A> permutes with all these subgroups, then the algorithm checks whether <A>H</A> is hypercentrally embedded in
<A>G</A> and that the Sylow <M>p</M>-subgroups of <M>H/H_G</M>  permute with all cyclic
<M>p</M>-subgroups of <M>G/H_G</M> for each prime <M>p</M> dividing the order of <M>G/H_G</M>. This is a sufficient condition for
permutability. 
</Description>
</ManSection>




<ManSection>
<Func Name="OneSubgroupNotPermutingWith" Arg="G, H" Comm="finds why a subgroup is not permutable"/>
<Attr Name="OneSubgroupNotPermutingWithInParent" Arg="H" Comm="finds why a subgroup is not permutable"/>

<Description>
This attribute finds a cyclic subgroup of <A>G</A> which does not permute
with <A>H</A>, that is, a subgroup which shows that <A>H</A> is not permutable in <A>G</A>. Recall that a subgroup <M>H</M> of a group <M>G</M> is <E>permutable</E> in
<M>G</M> if <M>H</M> permutes with all subgroups of&nbsp;<M>G</M>.
<P/>


<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);
Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> a:=Subgroup(g,[(1,2)(3,4)]);
Group([ (1,2)(3,4) ])
gap> b:=Subgroup(g,[(1,2,3)]);
Group([ (1,2,3) ])
gap> c:=Subgroup(g,[(1,2)]);
Group([ (1,2) ])
gap> IsPermutable(g,a);
false
gap> IsPermutable(g,b);
false
gap> IsPermutable(g,c);
false
gap> OneSubgroupNotPermutingWith(g,b);
Group([ (1,3,4) ])
gap> v:=Subgroup(g,[(1,2)(3,4),(1,3)(2,4)]);
Group([ (1,2)(3,4), (1,3)(2,4) ])
gap> OneSubgroupNotPermutingWith(g,v);
fail
gap> IsPermutable(g,b);
false
gap> IsPermutable(g,v);
true
]]></Example>
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SmallGroup(16,6);
<pc group of size 16 with 4 generators>
gap> h:=Subgroup(g,[g.2]);
Group([ f2 ])
gap> IsNormal(g,h);
false
gap> IsPermutable(g,h);
true
]]></Example>

</Description>
</ManSection>

Sometimes one does not require a subgroup to permute with all subgroups of
the group, but only with a selected family of subgroups of the
group. The general case is the following.
<P/>


<ManSection>
<Func Name="IsFPermutable" Arg="G, H, f" Comm="property, whether object is f-permutable" />

<Description>

In this function, <A>H</A> is a subgroup of <A>G</A> and <A>f</A> must be a list of subgroups of <A>G</A>. It returns <K>true</K> if <A>H</A> permutes with all members of
<A>f</A> and <K>false</K> otherwise. 
<P/>

This function uses the function <Ref Attr="OneFSubgroupNotPermutingWith"/>. Hence it tries
to use the values of <Ref Prop="IsPermutableInParent"/> and
<Ref Attr="OneSubgroupNotPermutingWithInParent" /> if one of them is set, and if it returns
<K>false</K> it tries to set the values of <Ref Prop="IsPermutableInParent"/> and
<Ref Attr="OneSubgroupNotPermutingWithInParent" />.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="OneFSubgroupNotPermutingWith" Arg="G, H, f"  Comm="finds a non f-permutable subgroup" />

<Description>
In this operation, <A>H</A> is a subgroup of <A>G</A> and <A>f</A> must be a list of subgroups of <A>G</A>. It returns a subgroup in <A>f</A> not permuting with <A>H</A> if
such a subgroup exists, and <K>fail</K> otherwise.
<P/>

This function tries to use the values of <Ref Prop="IsPermutableInParent" /> and
<Ref Attr="OneSubgroupNotPermutingWithInParent" /> if one of them is set. If it returns
<K>fail</K>, then it tries to set the value of <Ref Prop="IsPermutableInParent" /> and
<Ref Attr="OneSubgroupNotPermutingWithInParent" />.

<P/>

<Log>
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);
Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> a:=Subgroup(g,[(1,2,3,4),(1,3)]);
Group([ (1,2,3,4), (1,3) ])
gap> Size(a);
8
gap> OneFSubgroupNotPermutingWith(g,a,MaximalSubgroups(g));
Group([ (1,2), (3,4), (1,3)(2,4) ])
gap> IsFPermutable(g,a,MaximalSubgroups(g));
false
gap> HasIsPermutableInParent(a);
true
gap> IsPermutableInParent(a);
false
gap> HasOneSubgroupNotPermutingWithInParent(a);
true
gap> OneSubgroupNotPermutingWithInParent(a);
Group([ (1,2), (3,4), (1,3)(2,4) ])
gap> IsFPermutable(g,a,AllSubnormalSubgroups(g));
true
gap> OneFSubgroupNotPermutingWith(g,a,AllSubnormalSubgroups(g));
fail
gap> sylows:=g->Union(List(SylowSubgroups(g),
>           t->ConjugacyClassSubgroups(g,t)));
function( g ) ... end
gap> OneFSubgroupNotPermutingWith(g,a,sylows(g));
Group([ (3,4), (1,4)(2,3), (1,3)(2,4) ])
</Log>
</Description>
</ManSection>

The following functions can be considered as particular cases of the
previous function for some subgroup embedding functors. However, they
can be stored as <Q>in parent</Q> attributes or properties and in some
cases we have tried to give  more efficient code.
<P/>


<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsSPermutable" Arg="G, H" Comm="test for S-permutability" />
<Prop Name="IsSPermutableInParent" Arg="H" Comm="test for S-permutability" />
<Description>
This operation returns <K>true</K> if a subgroup <A>H</A> of <A>G</A> is S-permutable in <A>G</A>,
that is, <A>H</A> permutes with all Sylow subgroups of <A>G</A>, and returns <K>false</K> otherwise.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SmallGroup(8,3);
<pc group of size 8 with 3 generators>
gap> IsSPermutable(g,Subgroup(g,[g.1]));
true
gap> IsPermutable(g,Subgroup(g,[g.1]));
false
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="OneSylowSubgroupNotPermutingWith" Arg="G, H" Comm="finds why a subgroup is not S-permutable" />
<Attr Name="OneSylowSubgroupNotPermutingWithInParent" Arg="H" Comm="finds why a subgroup is not S-permutable" />

<Description>

The argument <A>H</A> must be a subgroup of <A>G</A>. If <A>H</A> is S-permutable in <A>G</A>, then it returns <K>fail</K>. Otherwise, it returns a Sylow subgroup of <A>G</A> which does not permute
with <A>H</A>. We say that a
subgroup <M>H</M> of a group <M>G</M> is S-permutable in <M>G</M> if <M>H</M> permutes
with all Sylow subgroups of&nbsp;<M>G</M>.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);;
gap> a:=Subgroup(g,[(1,2)(3,4)]);;
gap> OneSylowSubgroupNotPermutingWith(g,a);
Group([ (2,4,3) ])
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsSNPermutable" Arg="G, H" Comm="checks whether a subgroup is system normalizer permutable" />
<Attr Name="IsSNPermutableInParent" Arg="H" Comm="checks whether a subgroup is system normalizer permutable" />
<Description>
This operation returns <K>true</K> if <A>H</A> permutes with all system
normalisers of <A>G</A>, and <K>false</K> otherwise. Here <A>G</A>
must be a soluble group and <A>H</A> must be a subgroup of
<A>G</A>. If the function is applied to an insoluble group, it gives
an error.
</Description>

</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="OneSystemNormaliserNotPermutingWith" Arg="G, H" Comm="checks why a subgroup is not system normalizer permutable" />
<Attr Name="OneSystemNormaliserNotPermutingWithInParent" Arg="H" Comm="checks why a subgroup is not system normalizer permutable" />
<Description>

Here <A>G</A>
must be a soluble group and <A>H</A> must be a subgroup of <A>G</A>.
If <A>H</A> permutes with all system normalisers of <A>G</A>, then
this operation
returns <K>fail</K>. Otherwise, it returns a system normaliser <M>D</M> of <M>G</M> such that <M>H</M> does
not permute with <M>D</M>. If the group <A>G</A> is not soluble, then
it gives an error.

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=Group((1,2,3),(4,5,6),(1,2));
Group([ (1,2,3), (4,5,6), (1,2) ])
gap> a:=Subgroup(g,[(1,2,3)(4,5,6)]);
Group([ (1,2,3)(4,5,6) ])
gap> IsSNPermutable(g,a);
true
gap> IsSPermutable(g,a);
false
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<P/>

The next functions are not particular cases of <Ref Oper="IsFPermutable" /> or
<Ref Oper="OneFSubgroupNotPermutingWith" />, but we include them in the package because
every subgroup permuting with all its conjugates is subnormal (see
<Cite Key="Foguel97" />).
<P/>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsConjugatePermutable" Arg="G, H" Comm="checks whether the subgroup permutes with all its conjugates" />
<Prop Name="IsConjugatePermutableInParent" Arg="H" Comm="checks whether the subgroup permutes with all its conjugates" />

<Description>

This operation takes the value <K>true</K> if <A>H</A> permutes with all its
conjugates, and the value <K>false</K> otherwise.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);
Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> a:=Subgroup(g,[(1,2)(3,4)]);
Group([ (1,2)(3,4) ])
gap> IsPermutable(g,a);
false
gap> IsConjugatePermutable(g,a);
true
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="OneConjugateSubgroupNotPermutingWith" Arg="G, H" Comm="returns a conjugate of a subgroup which does not permute with it" />
<Attr Name="OneConjugateSubgroupNotPermutingWithInParent" Arg="H" Comm="returns a conjugate of a subgroup which does not permute with it" />
<Description>

This operation finds a conjugate subgroup of <A>H</A> which does not
permute with <A>H</A> if such a subgroup exists. If <A>H</A> permutes with all its conjugates, then this
operation returns <K>fail</K>.

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SmallGroup(16,7);
<pc group of size 16 with 4 generators>
gap> h:=Subgroup(g,[g.1*g.4]);
Group([ f1*f4 ])
gap> IsConjugatePermutable(g,h);
false
gap> OneConjugateSubgroupNotPermutingWith(g,h);
Group([ f1*f3 ])
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<P/>

Next we introduce some subgroup embedding functions related
to permutability which have proved to be useful in some
characterisations of soluble T-groups, PT-groups, and PST-groups. The
<Q>One</Q> functions return a value which proves that the corresponding
subgroup embedding property is false.
<P/>


<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsWeaklySPermutable" Arg="G, H" Comm="checks whether a subgroup is weakly S-permutable" />
<Prop Name="IsWeaklySPermutableInParent" Arg="H" Comm="checks whether a subgroup is weakly S-permutable" />

<Description>
The value returned by this operation is <K>true</K> when  <A>H</A> is a <E>weakly S-permutable</E>
subgroup of <A>G</A>, that is, <M>H</M> is S-permutable in <M>\langle H, H^g \rangle</M>
implies that <M>H</M> is S-permutable in <M>\langle H, g \rangle</M>, and <K>false</K>
otherwise.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="OneElementShowingNotWeaklySPermutable" Arg="G, H" Comm="returns why a subgroup is not weakly S-permutable" />
<Attr Name="OneElementShowingNotWeaklySPermutableInParent" Arg="H" Comm="returns why a subgroup is not weakly S-permutable" />
<Description>

If <A>H</A> is a weakly S-permutable subgroup of <A>G</A>, then this
operation returns <K>fail</K>. Otherwise, the value returned by this operation is an
element <M>g \in G</M> such that <A>H</A> is
S-permutable in <M>\langle H, H^g \rangle</M>, but <M>H</M> is not S-permutable
in <M>\langle H, g \rangle</M>. A subgroup <M>H</M> of a group <M>G</M> is said to be
weakly S-permutable if <M>H</M> is S-permutable in <M>\langle H,
H^g \rangle</M> implies that <M>H</M> is S-permutable in <M>\langle H, g \rangle</M>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsWeaklyPermutable" Arg="G, H" Comm="returns whether a subgroup is weakly permutable" />
<Prop Name="IsWeaklyPermutableInParent" Arg="H" Comm="returns whether a subgroup is weakly permutable" />

<Description>

This operation returns <K>true</K> if <A>H</A> is weakly permutable in <A>G</A>, and
<K>false</K> otherwise. A subgroup <M>H</M> of <M>G</M> is <E>weakly
permutable</E> if the fact that <M>H</M> is S-permutable in <M>\langle
H, H^g \rangle</M>, implies that <M>H</M> is S-permutable in <M>\langle H, g \rangle</M>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="OneElementShowingNotWeaklyPermutable" Arg="G, H" Comm="returns why a subgroup is not weakly permutable" />
<Attr Name="OneElementShowingNotWeaklyPermutableInParent" Arg="H" Comm="returns why a subgroup is not weakly permutable" />
<Description>

If <A>H</A> is a weakly permutable subgroup of <A>G</A>, then this
operation returns <K>fail</K>. Otherwise, the value returned by this operation is an element <M>g \in G</M> such that <A>H</A> is
permutable in <M>\langle H, H^g \rangle</M>, but <M>H</M> is not permutable
in <M>\langle H, g \rangle</M>. A subgroup <M>H</M> of a group <M>G</M> is said to be
<E>weakly permutable</E> if the fact that <M>H</M> is permutable in <M>\langle H,
H^g \rangle</M> implies that <M>H</M> is permutable in <M>\langle H, g \rangle</M>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsWeaklyNormal" Arg="G, H" Comm="returns whether a subgroup is weakly normal" />
<Prop Name="IsWeaklyNormalInParent" Arg="H" Comm="returns whether a subgroup is weakly normal" />

<Description>

This operation returns <K>true</K> if <A>H</A> is weakly normal in <A>G</A>, and
<K>false</K> otherwise. A subgroup <M>H</M> of <M>G</M> is <E>weakly normal</E> whenever if 
<M>H^g \leq {\rm N}_G(H)</M>, then <M>g \in {\rm N}_G(H)</M>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="OneElementShowingNotWeaklyNormal" Arg="G, H" Comm="returns why a subgroup is not weakly normal" />
<Attr Name="OneElementShowingNotWeaklyNormalInParent" Arg="H" Comm="returns why a subgroup is not weakly normal" />
<Description>

If <A>H</A> is a weakly normal subgruop of <A>G</A>, then this
function returns <K>fail</K>. Otherwise, the value returned by this operation is an element <M>g</M> such that <M>H^g\leq {\rm N}_G(H)</M> is a subgroup of <M>{\rm N}_G(H)</M> but <M>g \notin{\rm N}_G(H)</M>.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=DihedralGroup(8);
<pc group of size 8 with 3 generators>
gap> a:=Subgroup(g,[g.1]);
Group([ f1 ])
gap> IsWeaklySPermutable(g,a);
true
gap> IsWeaklyPermutable(g,a);
false
gap> x:=OneElementShowingNotWeaklyPermutable(g,a);
f2
gap> IsSubgroup(Normalizer(g,a),ConjugateSubgroup(a,x));
true
gap> x in Normalizer(g,a);
false
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsWithSubnormalizerCondition" Arg="G, H" Comm="checks whether a subgroup has the subnormalizer condition" />
<Prop Name="IsWithSubnormalizerConditionInParent" Arg="H" Comm="checks whether a subgroup has the subnormalizer condition" />
<Oper Name="IsWithSubnormaliserCondition" Arg="G, H" Comm="checks whether a subgroup has the subnormalizer condition" />
<Prop Name="IsWithSubnormaliserConditionInParent" Arg="H" Comm="checks whether a subgroup has the subnormalizer condition" />
<Description>

This operation returns <K>true</K> if the subgroup <M>H</M> satisfies the
subnormaliser condition in <M>G</M>, and <K>false</K> otherwise.
<P/>

A subgroup <M>H</M> is said to <E>satisfy the subnormaliser condition</E> in <M>G</M>
if the condition that <M>H</M> is subnormal in a subgroup <M>K</M> of
<M>G</M> implies that <M>H</M> is normal
in&nbsp;<M>K</M>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="OneSubgroupInWhichSubnormalNotNormal" Arg="G, H" Comm="returns why a subgroup does not have the subnormalizer condition" />
<Attr Name="OneSubgroupInWhichSubnormalNotNormalInParent" Arg="H" Comm="returns why a subgroup does not have the subnormalizer condition" />
<Description>

This function returns a subgroup <M>K</M> of <M>G</M> such that <M>H</M> is subnormal
in <M>K</M> and <M>H</M> is not normal in&nbsp;<M>K</M>, if this
subgroup exists; otherwise, it returns <K>fail</K>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsWithSubpermutizerCondition" Arg="G, H" Comm="checks whether a subgroup has the subpermutizer condition" />
<Prop Name="IsWithSubpermutizerConditionInParent" Arg="H" Comm="checks whether a subgroup has the subpermutizer condition" />
<Oper Name="IsWithSubpermutiserCondition" Arg="G, H" Comm="checks whether a subgroup has the subpermutiser condition" />
<Prop Name="IsWithSubpermutiserConditionInParent" Arg="H" Comm="checks whether a subgroup has the subpermutiser condition" />
<Description>
This operation returns <K>true</K> if the subgroup <M>H</M> satisfies the
subpermutiser condition in <M>G</M>, and <K>false</K> otherwise.
<P/>

A subgroup <M>H</M> is said to <E>satisfy the subpermutiser condition</E> in <M>G</M>
if the condition that <M>H</M> is subnormal in a subgroup <M>K</M> of
<M>G</M> implies that <M>H</M> is permutable
in&nbsp;<M>K</M>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="OneSubgroupInWhichSubnormalNotPermutable" Arg="G, H" Comm="returns why a subgroup does not have the subpermutizer condition" />
<Attr Name="OneSubgroupInWhichSubnormalNotPermutableInParent" Arg="H" Comm="returns why a subgroup does not have the subpermutizer condition" />
<Description>
This function returns a subgroup <M>K</M> of <M>G</M> such that <M>H</M> is subnormal
in <M>K</M> and <M>H</M> is not permutable in&nbsp;<M>K</M> if this
subgroup exists; otherwise it returns <K>fail</K>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsWithSSubpermutizerCondition" Arg="G, H" Comm="returns whether a subgroup has the S-subpermutizer condition" />
<Prop Name="IsWithSSubpermutizerConditionInParent" Arg="H" Comm="returns whether a subgroup has the S-subpermutizer condition" />
<Oper Name="IsWithSSubpermutiserCondition" Arg="G, H" Comm="returns whether a subgroup has the S-subpermutizer condition" />
<Prop Name="IsWithSSubpermutiserConditionInParent" Arg="H" Comm="returns whether a subgroup has the S-subpermutizer condition" />
<Description>
This operation returns <K>true</K> if the subgroup <M>H</M> satisfies the
S-subpermutiser condition in <M>G</M>, and <K>false</K> otherwise.
<P/>

A subgroup <M>H</M> is said to <E>satisfy the S-subpermutiser condition</E> in <M>G</M>
if the condition that <M>H</M> is subnormal in a subgroup <M>K</M> of
<M>G</M> implies that <M>H</M> is S-permutable
in&nbsp;<M>K</M>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="OneSubgroupInWhichSubnormalNotSPermutable" Arg="G, H" Comm="returns why a subgroup does not have the S-subpermutizer condition" />
<Attr Name="OneSubgroupInWhichSubnormalNotSPermutableInParent" Arg="H" Comm="returns why a subgroup does not have the S-subpermutizer condition" />

<Description>

This function returns a subgroup <M>K</M> of <M>G</M> such that <M>H</M> is subnormal
in <M>K</M> and <M>H</M> is not S-permutable in&nbsp;<M>K</M> if such
a subgroup exists; otherwise it returns <K>fail</K>.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SmallGroup(324,160);
<pc group of size 324 with 6 generators>
gap> a:=Subgroup(g,[g.3,g.5]);
Group([ f3, f5 ])
gap> IsWithSubnormalizerCondition(g,a);
true
gap> IsWeaklyNormal(g,a);
false
gap> IsWeaklySPermutable(g,a);
false
gap> x:=OneElementShowingNotWeaklyNormal(g,a);
f1
gap> ConjugateSubgroup(a,x)=a;
false
gap> IsSubset(Normalizer(g,a),ConjugateSubgroup(a,x));
true
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>










</Section>

</Chapter>





<Chapter><Heading>T-groups, PT-groups, and PST-groups</Heading>
This chapter explains the functions to check whether a given group is
a T-group, a PT-group, or a PST-group.
<P/>

Recall that a group <M>G</M> is:
<List>
<Mark>a T-group</Mark><Item>when every subnormal subgroup of <M>G</M> is normal,</Item>
<Mark>a PT-group</Mark><Item>when every subnormal subgroup of <M>G</M> is permutable,</Item>
<Mark>a PST-group</Mark><Item> when every subnormal subgroup of <M>G</M> is S-permutable.</Item>
</List>
<P/>

We also present functions to identify groups in other classes related
to these ones. 
<P/>

The <Q>One</Q> functions are defined to provide examples of subgroups or
elements showing that a group theoretical property for a group or for
a subgroup is false.
<P/>


<Section Label="permut-embedding-properties-one"><Heading><Q>One</Q> functions</Heading>

<ManSection>
<Attr Name="OneSubnormalNonNormalSubgroup" Arg="G" Comm="why a group is not a T-group" />
<Description>

<Ref Attr="OneSubnormalNonNormalSubgroup" /> returns a subnormal subgroup of defect&nbsp;<M>2</M> which is
not normal in the group <A>G</A>, if such a subgroup exists. If such a subgroup does not exist
because the group is a T-group, it returns
<K>fail</K>.
<P/>

A T-group is a group in which normality is transitive, that is, if <M>H</M>
is a normal subgroup of <M>K</M> and <M>K</M> is a normal subgroup of <M>G</M>, then 
<M>H</M> is a normal subgroup of&nbsp;<M>G</M>. Finite T-groups are the groups in
which every subnormal subgroup is normal.
<P/>

This function tries to set the property <Ref Prop="IsTGroup" /> to <K>true</K> or <K>false</K> according
to its result.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SmallGroup(320,152);
<pc group of size 320 with 7 generators>
gap> x:=OneSubnormalNonNormalSubgroup(g);
Group([ f2, f3, f5, f7 ])
gap> IsNormal(g,x);
false
gap> IsSubnormal(g,x);
true
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Attr Name="OneSubnormalNonPermutableSubgroup" Arg="G" Comm="returns a non-permutable subgroup" />
<Description>
<Ref Attr="OneSubnormalNonPermutableSubgroup" /> returns a subnormal subgroup which is
not permutable in the group <A>G</A>, if such a subgroup exists. If such a subgroup does not
exist because the group is a PT-group, it returns
<K>fail</K>.
<P/>

A group <M>G</M> is a PT-group when permutability is a transitive relation
in <M>G</M>, that is, if <M>H</M> is a permutable subgroup of <M>K</M> and <M>K</M> is a
permutable subgroup of <M>G</M>, then <M>H</M> is a permutable subgroupof&nbsp;<M>G</M>. This is equivalent in finite groups to affirming that every
subnormal subgroup of <M>G</M> is permutable.
<P/>

This function tries to set the property <Ref Prop="IsPTGroup" /> to <K>true</K> or <K>false</K> according
to its result.
<P/>

Since this function checks all subnormal subgroups for permutability,
it may take a long time if there are many subnormal subgroups.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SmallGroup(320,152);
<pc group of size 320 with 7 generators>
gap> OneSubnormalNonPermutableSubgroup(g);
fail
gap> IsPTGroup(g);
true
gap> g:=SmallGroup(8,3);
<pc group of size 8 with 3 generators>
gap> OneSubnormalNonPermutableSubgroup(g);
Group([ f1*f3 ])
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Attr Name="OneSubnormalNonSPermutableSubgroup" Arg="G" Comm="returns a non-S-permutable subgroup" />
<Description>

<Ref Attr="OneSubnormalNonSPermutableSubgroup" /> returns a subnormal subgroup of defect&nbsp;<M>2</M> which is
not S-permutable in <A>G</A>, if such a subgroup exists. If such a subgroup does not exist
because the group is a PST-group, it returns
<K>fail</K>.
<P/>

A group <M>G</M> is a PST-group when S-permutability (Sylow permutability) is a transitive relation
in <M>G</M>, that is, if <M>H</M> is an S-permutable subgroup of <M>K</M> and <M>K</M> is an
S-permutable subgroup of <M>G</M>, then <M>H</M> is an S-permutable subgroup of&nbsp;<M>G</M>. This is equivalent in finite groups to affirming that every
subnormal subgroup of <M>G</M> is S-permutable. By a result of
Ballester-Bolinches, Esteban-Romero, and Ragland
<Cite Key="BallesterEstebanRagland07" />, it is enough to
check this last condition for all subnormal subgroups of defect&nbsp;<M>2</M>.
<P/>

This function tries to set the property <Ref Attr="IsPSTGroup" /> to <K>true</K> or <K>false</K> according
to its result.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=AlternatingGroup(4);
Alt( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> OneSubnormalNonSPermutableSubgroup(g);
Group([ (1,2)(3,4) ])
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Attr Name="OneSubnormalNonConjugatePermutableSubgroup" Arg="G" Comm="finds a subnormal subgroup not permuting with all its conjugates" />
<Description>
This function finds a subnormal subgroup <M>H</M> which does not permute
with all its conjugates, if such a subgroup exist; otherwise, it
returns <K>fail</K>.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=AlternatingGroup(4);
Alt( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> OneSubnormalNonConjugatePermutableSubgroup(g);
fail
gap> g:=DihedralGroup(16);
<pc group of size 16 with 4 generators>
gap> OneSubnormalNonConjugatePermutableSubgroup(g);
Group([ f1*f4 ])
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);
Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> OneSubnormalNonConjugatePermutableSubgroup(g);
fail
gap> OneSubnormalNonPermutableSubgroup(g);
Group([ (1,2)(3,4) ])
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Attr Name="OneSubnormalNonSNPermutableSubgroup" Arg="G" Comm="finds a subgroup not permuting with a system normalizer" />
<Description>

This attribute returns a subnormal subgroup <M>H</M> of the soluble group
<M>G</M> such that <M>H</M> does not permute with a system normaliser
if such a subgroup exists; otherwise, it returns <K>fail</K>. This
system normaliser is obtained with the function <Ref
Func="SystemNormalizer" BookName="Format" /> of the
<Package>Format</Package> package.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);
Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> OneSubnormalNonSNPermutableSubgroup(g);
Group([ (1,3)(2,4) ])
gap> g:=Group((1,2,3)(4,5,6),(1,2));
Group([ (1,2,3)(4,5,6), (1,2) ])
gap> OneSubnormalNonSNPermutableSubgroup(g);
fail
gap> OneSubnormalNonSPermutableSubgroup(g); 
Group([ (1,2,3)(4,6,5) ])
]]></Example>

</Description>
</ManSection>

</Section>
<Section Label="T-properties"><Heading>Group properties related to permutability</Heading>

The next function names correspond to properties.
<P/>

<ManSection>
<Prop Name="IsTGroup" Arg="G" Comm="checks whether the group is a T-group" />
<Description>

This function returns <K>true</K> if <A>G</A> is a T-group, and <K>false</K>
otherwise.
<P/>

T-groups are the groups in which normality is a transitive relation,
that is, if <M>H</M> is a subgroup of <M>K</M> and <M>K</M> is a subgroup of <M>G</M>,
then <M>H</M> is a subgroup of&nbsp;<M>G</M>. In the finite case, they are the groups
in which every subnormal subgroup is normal.
<P/>

For soluble groups, the algorithm checks that for every prime
<M>p</M> dividing its order, <M>G</M> is <M>p</M>-nilpotent and has a Dedekind Sylow
<M>p</M>-subgroup or <M>G</M> has an abelian Sylow <M>p</M>-subgroup <M>P</M> and
every subgroup of <M>P</M> is normal in <M>{\rm N}_G(P)</M>.
<P/>

For insoluble groups, the function checks
whether the group is an
SC-group with the function <Ref Prop="IsSCGroup" />, because
PT-groups are SC-groups. Since the methods
for insoluble groups depend on the computation of a chief series with
the function <Ref Oper="ChiefSeries" BookName="Ref" />, they might not
be available if the group is not given as a permutation group. Then 
it is checked that every subnormal subgroup of
defect&nbsp;<M>2</M> is normal with the help of the function
<Ref Oper="OneSubnormalNonNormalSubgroup" />. The methods based on the ideas of
<Cite Key="BallesterBeidlemanHeineken03-illinois" />,
<Cite Key="BallesterBeidlemanHeineken03-commalg" />, and
<Cite Key="BeidlemanHeineken03-jgt" /> have not been implemented so far because they
require the computation of quotients by all normal subgroups, which
could be a time-consuming task.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SmallGroup(40,4);
<pc group of size 40 with 4 generators>
gap> IsTGroup(g);
true
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(3);
Sym( [ 1 .. 3 ] )
gap> IsTGroup(g);
true
]]></Example>
<P/>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Prop Name="IsPTGroup" Arg="G" Comm="checks whether the group is a PT-group" />
<Description>


This property takes the value <K>true</K> if <A>G</A> is a PT-group, and the
value <K>false</K>
otherwise.
<P/>

For a soluble group <M>G</M>, the function checks whether for all primes <M>p</M>,
<M>G</M> is <M>p</M>-nilpotent and has an Iwasawa Sylow <M>p</M>-subgroup or <M>G</M>
has an abelian Sylow <M>p</M>-subgroup and it satisfies the property <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  C}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>C_p</M></Alt>
(that is, every subgroup of a Sylow <M>p</M>-subgroup <M>P</M> of <M>G</M> is normal
in the Sylow normaliser <M>{\rm N}_G(P)</M>).
<P/>

For insoluble groups, the function checks that the group is an
SC-group with the function <Ref Prop="IsSCGroup" />, because PT-groups
are SC-groups. Since the methods for insoluble groups depend on the
computation of a chief series with the function <Ref
Oper="ChiefSeries" BookName="Ref" />, they might not be available if
the group is not given as a permutation group. Then
it uses the function <Ref Attr="OneSubnormalNonPermutableSubgroup" /> to check
whether or not every subnormal subgroup is permutable. The methods based on the ideas of
<Cite Key="BallesterBeidlemanHeineken03-illinois" />,
<Cite Key="BallesterBeidlemanHeineken03-commalg" />, and
<Cite Key="BeidlemanHeineken03-jgt" /> have not been implemented so far because they
require the computation of quotients by all normal subgroups, which
could be a time-consuming task.
<P/>


<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SmallGroup(1323,37);
<pc group of size 1323 with 5 generators>
gap> IsPTGroup(g);
true
gap> IsTGroup(g);
false
gap> OneSubnormalNonNormalSubgroup(g);
Group([ f2*f3, f4, f5 ])
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Prop Name="IsPSTGroup" Arg="G" Comm="checks whether a group is a PST-group" />
<Description>

This function returns true if the group <A>G</A> is a
PST-group, and false otherwise.
<P/>

A finite group <M>G</M> is a PST-group if S-permutability (Sylow-permutability) is a transitive
relation in <M>G</M>, that is, if <M>H</M> is S-permutable in <M>K</M> and <M>K</M> is
S-permutable in <M>G</M>, then <M>H</M> is S-permutable in&nbsp;<M>G</M>. This is
equivalent to affirming that every subnormal subgroup of <M>G</M> is S-permutable in&nbsp;<M>G</M>.
<P/>

For a soluble group <M>G</M>, the function checks whether for all primes <M>p</M>,
<M>G</M> is <M>p</M>-nilpotent, or <M>G</M>
has an abelian Sylow <M>p</M>-subgroup and <M>G</M> satisfies the property
<Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  C}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>C_p</M></Alt>
(that is, every subgroup of a Sylow <M>p</M>-subgroup <M>P</M> of <M>G</M> is normal
in the Sylow normaliser <M>{\rm N}_G(P)</M>)
<P/>

For insoluble groups, the function checks whether the group is an
SC-group with the function <Ref Prop="IsSCGroup" />, because
PST-groups are SC-groups. Since the methods
for insoluble groups depend on the computation of a chief series with
the function <Ref Oper="ChiefSeries" BookName="Ref" />, they might not
be available if the group is not given as a permutation group. Then 
it uses the function <Ref Attr="OneSubnormalNonSPermutableSubgroup" /> to check
whether or not every subnormal subgroup of defect&nbsp;<M>2</M> is
S-permutable. The methods based on the ideas of
<Cite Key="BallesterBeidlemanHeineken03-illinois" />,
<Cite Key="BallesterBeidlemanHeineken03-commalg" />, and
<Cite Key="BeidlemanHeineken03-jgt" /> have not been implemented so far because they
require the computation of quotients by all normal subgroups, which
could be a time-consuming task.
<P/>


<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SmallGroup(24,6);
<pc group of size 24 with 4 generators>
gap> IsPSTGroup(g);
true
gap> IsPTGroup(g);
false
gap> OneSubnormalNonPermutableSubgroup(g);
Group([ f1*f3, f4 ])
gap> g:=SmallGroup(24,6);
<pc group of size 24 with 4 generators>
gap> IsPSTGroup(g);
true
gap> IsPTGroup(g);
false
gap> OneSubnormalNonPermutableSubgroup(g);
Group([ f1*f3, f4 ])
gap> OneSubgroupNotPermutingWith(g,last);
Group([ f1*f2 ])
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Prop Name="IsCPTGroup" Arg="G" Comm="checks whether every subnormal subgroup is conjugate-permutable" />
<Description>

This property returns true if every subnormal subgroup of <A>G</A> permutes
with all its conjugates, and false otherwise.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);
Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> IsCPTGroup(g);
true
gap> IsPTGroup(g);
false
gap> IsPSTGroup(g);
false
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>
<ManSection>
<Prop Name="IsPSNTGroup" Arg="G" Comm="checks whether every subnormal subgroup permutes with every system normalizer" />
<Description>

This property takes the value <K>true</K> if every subnormal subgroup of
the soluble group <M>G</M> permutes with every system normaliser of <M>G</M>,
and <K>false</K> otherwise. If the function is applied to an insoluble
group, it gives an error.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=Group((1,2,3)(4,5,6),(1,3));
Group([ (1,2,3)(4,5,6), (1,3) ])
gap> IsPSTGroup(g);
false
gap> IsPSNTGroup(g);
true
gap> IsCPTGroup(g);
true
gap> g:=SmallGroup(16,7);
<pc group of size 16 with 4 generators>
gap> IsPSTGroup(g);
true
gap> IsCPTGroup(g);
false
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);
Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> IsPSNTGroup(g);
false
gap> IsCPTGroup(g);
true
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>
</Section>
</Chapter>
<Chapter><Heading>Local Functions in the <Package>PERMUT</Package> Package</Heading>



In the study of permutability, the usage of local characterisations
has become a useful tool to describe the classes of T-groups,
PT-groups, and PST-groups. In this chapter we present some local
characterisations of these classes and some functions which allow to
check whether or not a group given in &GAP; satisfies these
conditions.
<P/>

A <E>local</E> description of group-theoretical property consists of
expressing it as the conjunction of some properties depending on a prime
<M>p</M>, usually related to the behaviour of <M>p</M>-elements, <M>p</M>-subgroups,
or <M>p</M>-chief factors,  for all primes <M>p</M>.
<P/>



<Section Label="solvable"><Heading>A Local Function for Supersolubility</Heading>
The &GAP; library does not contain methods to check whether a group <M>G</M> is <M>p</M>-supersoluble, where <M>p</M> is a prime number. We include such a function in the <Package>PERMUT</Package> package.

<ManSection>
<Func Name="IsPSupersolvable" Arg="G, p" Comm="checks whether the group is p-supersolvable" />
<Func Name="IsPSupersoluble" Arg="G, p" Comm="checks whether the group is p-supersolvable" />

<Description>

This function returns <K>true</K> if the group <A>G</A> is <M>p</M>-supersoluble, and
<K>false</K> otherwise, where <A>p</A> is a prime number. This function is not defined in &GAP;. The
method we have implemented for finite groups includes checking whether the
group is supersoluble (in this case, it must return <K>true</K>). If the
group is not soluble, it computes a chief series and checks whether
all chief factors have order <M>p</M> or have order not divisible
by&nbsp;<M>p</M>.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=Group((1,2,3,4,5,6,7), (8,9,10,11,12,13,14), (15,16,17,18,19,20,21),
> (22,23,24,25,26,27,28), (29,30,31,32,33,34,35),
> (1,8,15,22,29)(2,9,16,23,30)(3,10,17,24,31)(4,11,18,25,32)(5,12,19,26,
>     33)(6,13,20,27,34)(7,14,21,28,35),
> (1,8)(2,9)(3,10)(4,11)(5,12)(6,13)(7,14)); #C7 wr S5
<permutation group with 7 generators>
gap> IsPSupersolvable(g,7);
false
gap> IsPSupersolvable(g,11);
true
]]></Example>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=DirectProduct(PSL(2,7),
>     Group((1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11), (2,5,6,10,4)(3,9,11,8,7)));
Group([ (3,7,5)(4,8,6), (1,2,6)(3,4,8), (9,10,11,12,13,14,15,16,17,18,19),
  (10,13,14,18,12)(11,17,19,16,15) ])
gap> IsPNilpotent(g,5);
true
gap> IsPNilpotent(g,11);
false
gap> IsPSupersolvable(g,11);
true
gap> IsPNilpotent(g,3);
false
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>
</Section>
<Section Label="local-T-groups"><Heading>Local functions for T-groups, PT-groups, and PST-groups</Heading>


The following functions correspond to local description of the
classes of soluble T-groups, PT-groups, and PST-groups. Most of the
known useful local characterisations of these classes of groups can be
seen to be equivalent to one of them, either in the universe or all
finite groups or in the universe of all finite <M>p</M>-soluble
groups. By a local characterisation of a group-theoretical property
<Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  R}</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>R</M></Alt> we
mean a group-theoretical property <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  R}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>R_p</M></Alt> for each prime <M>p</M> such that a
group satisfies <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  R}</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>R</M></Alt> if and only if it satisfies <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  R}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>R_p</M></Alt> for
all primes <M>p</M>.

<ManSection>
<Func Name="IsCp" Arg="G, p" Comm="checks whether the group satisfies Cp" />

<Description>
This function returns <K>true</K> if the group <A>G</A> satisfies the property
<Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  C}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>C_p</M></Alt>, where <M>p</M> is a
  prime number, and <K>false</K> otherwise.

<P />
A group <M>G</M> satisfies <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  C}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>C_p</M></Alt>
when every subgroup <M>H</M> of a Sylow <M>p</M>-subgroup <M>P</M> of <M>G</M> is normal
in the corresponding Sylow normaliser <M>{\rm N}_G(P)</M>. This property was
introduced by Robinson in <Cite Key="Robinson68" />. A group <M>G</M> is a soluble
PST-group if and only if it satisfies <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  C}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>C_p</M></Alt> for all primes <M>p</M>.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=AlternatingGroup(5);
Alt( [ 1 .. 5 ] )
gap> IsCp(g,3);
true
gap> IsCp(g,5);
true
gap> IsCp(g,7);
true
gap> IsCp(g,2);
false
gap> g:=SmallGroup(200,44); # semidirect product of Q8 with C5xC5
<pc group of size 200 with 5 generators>
gap> IsCp(g,5);
false
gap> IsCp(g,2);
true
]]></Example>
<P/>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="IsXp" Arg="G, p" Comm="checks whether the group satisfies Xp" />
<Description>

This function returns <K>true</K> if <A>G</A> satisfies <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  X}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>X_p</M></Alt>, where <M>p</M>
is a prime, and <K>false</K> otherwise.
<P/>

A group <M>G</M> satisfies <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  X}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>X_p</M></Alt> when for every subgroup <M>H</M> of a Sylow
<M>p</M>-subgroup <M>P</M> of <M>G</M>, <M>H</M> is permutable in <M>{\rm N}_G(P)</M>. This
property was introduced by Beidleman, Brewster, and Robinson in
<Cite Key="BeidlemanBrewsterRobinson99" />. A group <M>G</M> is a soluble PT-group
if and only if <M>G</M> satisfies <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  X}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>X_p</M></Alt> for all primes <M>p</M>.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SmallGroup(189,7);
<pc group of size 189 with 4 generators>
gap> IsXp(g,3);
true
gap> IsXp(g,7);
true
gap> IsPTGroup(g);
true
gap> IsCp(g,3);
false
gap> IsTGroup(g);
false
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="IsYp" Arg="G, p" Comm="checks whether a group satisfies Yp" />
<Description>

This function returns <K>true</K> if <A>G</A> satisfies <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  Y}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>Y_p</M></Alt>, where <M>p</M>
is a prime, and <K>false</K> otherwise.
<P/>

A group <M>G</M> satisfies <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  X}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>Y_p</M></Alt> when for every two subgroups <M>H</M> and
<M>K</M> with <M>H\leq K</M>, <M>H</M> is S-permutable in <M>{\rm N}_G(P)</M>. This property
was introduced by Ballester-Bolinches and Esteban-Romero in
<Cite Key="BallesterEsteban02-sylper1" />. A group <M>G</M> is a soluble PST-group
if and only if <M>G</M> satisfies <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  Y}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>Y_p</M></Alt> for all primes <M>p</M>.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SmallGroup(200,43); # semidirect product of D8 with C5xC5
<pc group of size 200 with 5 generators>
gap> IsCp(g,2);
false
gap> IsXp(g,2);
false
gap> IsYp(g,2);
true
gap> g:=Group((1,2,3)(4,5,6),(1,2));
Group([ (1,2,3)(4,5,6), (1,2) ])
gap> IsYp(g,3);
false
gap> IsYp(g,2);
true
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

</Section>
<Section Label="aux-local"><Heading>Auxiliary Functions for T-groups, PT-groups, and PST-groups</Heading>

The following functions are used to check whether or not a group is a
soluble T-group, PT-group, or PST-group.
<P/>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="IsAbCp" Arg="G, p" Comm="checks whether a group has abelian Sylow p-subgroups and satisfies Cp" />
<Description>

This function returns <K>true</K> if <A>G</A> has an abelian Sylow <A>p</A>-subgroup
<A>p</A> such that every subgroup of <M>P</M> is normal in the Sylow normaliser
<M>{\rm N}_G(P)</M>, and <K>false</K> otherwise.
<P/>

This function is used to characterise soluble PST-groups: a group <M>G</M>
is a soluble PST-group if and only if <M>G</M> satisfies <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  Y}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>Y_p</M></Alt> for all
primes <M>p</M>, and a group <M>G</M> satisfies <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  Y}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>Y_p</M></Alt> if and only if <M>G</M>
is <M>p</M>-nilpotent or <M>G</M> has an abelian Sylow <M>p</M>-subgroup and
satisfies <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  C}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>C_p</M></Alt>. A group <M>G</M> satisfies <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  C}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>C_p</M></Alt> if and only if every
subgroup of a Sylow <M>p</M>-subgroup <M>P</M> of <M>G</M> is normal in the Sylow
normaliser <M>{\rm N}_G(P)</M>. Therefore this function checks whether <M>G</M>
has an abelian Sylow <M>p</M>-subgroup and <M>G</M> satisfies <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>{\cal
  C}_p</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>C_p</M></Alt>.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=AlternatingGroup(5);
Alt( [ 1 .. 5 ] )
gap> IsAbCp(g,5);
true
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="IsDedekindSylow" Arg="G, p" Comm="checks whether the group has Dedekind Sylow subgroups" />

<Description>

This function returns <K>true</K> if a Sylow <A>p</A>-subgroup of <A>G</A> is
Dedekind, else it returns <K>false</K>.
<P/>

A group <M>G</M> is Dedekind when every subgroup of <M>G</M> is normal. If <M>p</M>
is a prime, a Dedekind <M>p</M>-group (see for example 2.3.12 in
<Cite Key="Schmidt94" />) is abelian or a
direct product of a quaternion group of order <M>8</M> and an elementary
abelian <M>2</M>-group. Obviously, a <M>p</M>-group is Dedekind if and only if
it is a T-group.
<P/>

The algorithm used in this function to test whether a non-abelian
<M>2</M>-group satisfies this condition checks that the Frattini subgroup
of a Sylow <M>2</M>-subgroup <M>P</M> of <M>G</M> has order <M>2</M> and that the centre
of <M>P</M> has exponent <M>2</M> and index <M>4</M>. In this case, it computes the
natural epimorphism from <M>P</M> to <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>P/{\rm Z}(P)</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>P/Z(P)</M></Alt> and it checks that the
preimages of the generators of <Alt Only="LaTeX"><M>P/{\rm Z}(P)</M></Alt><Alt Not="LaTeX"><M>P/Z(P)</M></Alt> under the natural
epimorphism have order <M>4</M>. If all these conditions hold, then the
Sylow <M>2</M>-subgroup is Dedekind, otherwise it is not.
<P/>

This function tries to set the property <Ref Prop="IsTGroup" /> to <K>true</K> or <K>false</K> for
the Sylow <M>p</M>-subgroup.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=DirectProduct(SmallGroup(8,4),CyclicGroup(5));
<pc group of size 40 with 4 generators>
gap> IsDedekindSylow(g,2);
true
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="IwasawaTripleWithSubgroup" Arg="G, X, p" Comm="computes an Iwasawa triple with a given subgroup" />

<Description>

This function returns an Iwasawa triple for a <A>p</A>-group <A>G</A> such that
<A>X</A> is a member of it, if such a triple exists, and <K>fail</K> otherwise. This function is used as an auxiliary function
to compute an Iwasawa triple for a group <A>G</A>.
<P/>

An Iwasawa triple for a <M>p</M>-group <M>G</M> is a triple <M>(X,b,s)</M> such that
<M>X</M> is an abelian normal subgroup of <M>G</M> with cyclic quotient, <M>b</M> is
a generator of a supplement to <M>X</M> in <M>G</M>, and <M>b</M> induces a power
automorphism in <M>X</M> of the form <M>x\to x^{1+p^s}</M>. A theorem of
Iwasawa states that a <M>p</M>-group <M>G</M> has a modular subgroup lattice
(or, equivalently, <M>G</M> has all subgroups permutable) if
and only if <M>G</M> is a direct product of a quaternion group of order&nbsp;<M>8</M>
and an elementary abelian <M>2</M>-group or <M>G</M> has an Iwasawa triple
<M>(X,b,s)</M> with <M>s \geq 2</M>.
<P/>

The construction of the Iwasawa triple takes a generator <M>b</M> of a
cyclic supplement to <M>X</M> in&nbsp;<M>G</M>. Then we consider a generator <M>a</M> of
<M>X</M> of the largest possible order and find an element <M>c</M> of <M>\langle
b \rangle</M> and an element <M>s</M> such that <M>a^c = a^{1+p^s}</M>. If such an
element does not exist, the function returns <K>fail</K>. For this element,
it checks whether for all generators <M>t</M> of <M>X</M>, the equality
<M>t^c = t^{1+p^s}</M> holds. If this holds, it returns the triple <M>(X, c,
s)</M>; otherwise it returns <K>fail</K>.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> e:=ExtraspecialGroup(27,9);
<pc group of size 27 with 3 generators>
gap> IwasawaTripleWithSubgroup(e,Subgroup(e,[e.1,e.3]),3);
[ Group([ f1, f3 ]), f2, 1 ]
]]></Example>
<P/>
</Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
<Attr Name="IwasawaTriple" Arg="G" Comm="computes an Iwasawa triple for a p-group" />
<Description>

This function computes an Iwasawa triple for the <M>p</M>-group
<A>G</A>, if it exists. If <A>G</A>
is not Iwasawa, the function returns <K>fail</K>. If <A>G</A> is a
direct product of an elementary abelian <M>2</M>-group and a quaternion
group of order&nbsp;<M>8</M>, it returns an empty list. If <A>G</A> is Iwasawa, then
the function returns an Iwasawa triple for <A>G</A>. An Iwasawa triple for
a group <A>G</A> is a triple <M>(X, b, s)</M> where <M>X</M> is an abelian normal
subgroup of <M>G</M> such that <M>G/X</M> is cyclic, <M>b</M> is a generator of a
cyclic supplement to <M>X</M> in <M>G</M>, and <M>s</M> is an integer such that for
all <M>x \in X</M>, <M>x^b = x^{1+p^s}</M>. A theorem of Iwasawa states that a
<M>p</M>-group <M>G</M> has a modular subgroup lattice (or, equivalently, <M>G</M>
has all subgroups permutable) if and only if <M>G</M> is a
direct product of an elementary abelian <M>2</M>-group and a quaternion
group of order&nbsp;<M>8</M> or <M>G</M> has an Iwasawa triple <M>(X,b,s)</M> with <M>s \geq 2</M> if <M>p = 2</M>.
<P/>

The method followed to find an Iwasawa triple for non-abelian
non-Dedekind groups begins with the whole
group <M>G</M>. If the group is abelian, it returns the Iwasawa triple
<M>(G,1,\log_p\exp(G))</M>. If it is not abelian, it constructs a list <M>l</M>
formed by&nbsp;<M>G</M>. For every element <M>N</M> of <M>l</M>, it takes the maximal
subgroups of <M>N</M> which are normal in <M>G</M> and give cyclic quotient. If
any of these subgroups is a member of an Iwasawa triple, it is
computed with the function <Ref Func="IwasawaTripleWithSubgroup" /> and the value is
returned. If not, <M>N</M> is removed from the <M>l</M> and these maximal
subgroups of <M>N</M> are added to <M>l</M>. This follows until an Iwasawa triple is
found or the list <M>l</M> is empty. Since normal subgroups with cyclic
quotient are contained in a unique maximal chain, no subgroup appears
twice in this algorithm.
<P/>

The algorithm also takes into account the fact that a Iwasawa group of
exponent&nbsp;<M>4</M> must be abelian or a direct product of a quaternion group
of order&nbsp;<M>8</M> and an elementary abelian <M>2</M>-group.
<P/>

For the trivial group, it returns the triple composed by the trivial
group, its identity element, and the prime&nbsp;<M>3</M>.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> e:=ExtraspecialGroup(27,3);
<pc group of size 27 with 3 generators>
gap> IwasawaTriple(e);
fail
gap> e:=ExtraspecialGroup(27,9);
<pc group of size 27 with 3 generators>
gap> IwasawaTriple(e);
[ Group([ f1, f3 ]), f2, 1 ]
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="IsIwasawaSylow" Arg="G, p" Comm="checks whether the group has an Iwasawa Sylow p-subgroup" />
<Description>

This function returns <K>true</K> if <A>G</A> has an Iwasawa (modular) Sylow
<A>p</A>-subgroup, and <K>false</K> otherwise.
<P/>

Recall that a <M>p</M>-group <M>P</M> has a modular subgroup lattice, or is an
Iwasawa group, when all subgroups of <M>P</M> are permutable. It is clear
that a <M>p</M>-group has a modular subgroup lattice if and only if it is a
T-group.
<P/>


The implementation of this function begins by searching for a pair of subgroups that do not permute. In this case, the function returns <K>false</K>. The maximum number of pairs to be checked here is controlled by the variable <Ref Var="PermutMaxTries" />, which is assigned to <M>10</M> by default. If no such pair is found, the algorithm looks for an Iwasawa triple for a
Sylow <M>p</M>-subgroup <M>P</M> of&nbsp;<M>G</M>. If there exists one such triple <M>(X,b,s)</M> with <M>s \geq 2</M> when
<M>p = 2</M> or the group is a direct product of a quaternion group of
order&nbsp;<M>8</M> and an elementary abelian <M>2</M>-group, then it 
returns <K>true</K>; else it returns <K>false</K>.
<P/>

The values of the attributes <Ref Prop="IsPTGroup" /> and <Ref Prop="IsTGroup" /> for <M>P</M> are set
by the function.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> e:=ExtraspecialGroup(27,9);
<pc group of size 27 with 3 generators>
gap> IsIwasawaSylow(e,3);
true
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

</Section>
</Chapter>
<Chapter><Heading>Totally and Mutually Permutable Products</Heading>
<P/>

In recent years, many authors have considered totally and
mutually permutable subgroups. Recall that two subgroups <M>A</M> and <M>B</M>
of a group <M>G</M> are <E>totally permutable</E> if every subgroup of <M>A</M>
permutes with every subgroup of <M>B</M>, and they are <E>mutually
permutable</E> if every subgroup of <M>A</M> permutes with <M>B</M> and every
subgroup of <M>B</M> permutes with <M>A</M>.
<P/>

We have defined some <Q>One</Q> functions which give a pair of
subgroups which do not permute and prove that two subgroups fail to
have a certain property.
<P/>

We have also defined some functions to work with totally and mutually
<M>f</M>-permutable subgroups, where <M>f</M> is a subgroup embedding functor.
<P/>

The functions of this chapter are defined in a preliminary state.
<P/>

<Section><Heading>Functions for Mutually and Totally Permutable Products</Heading>

<ManSection>

<Func Name="AreMutuallyPermutableSubgroups" Arg="[G, ]A, B" Comm="checks whether two subgroups are mutually permutable" />
<Description>
This function returns <K>true</K> if the subgroups <M>A</M> and <M>B</M> of <M>G</M> are
mutually permutable
subgroups, that is, every subgroup of <M>A</M> permutes with <M>B</M> and every
subgroup of <M>B</M> permutes with <M>A</M>, and <K>false</K> otherwise. The method
used here checks only that <M>A</M> permutes with all cyclic subgroups of
<M>B</M> and that <M>B</M> permutes with all cyclic subgroups of <M>A</M>.
<P/>

The method with two arguments assume that <M>A</M> and <M>B</M> have a common
supergroup.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="OnePairShowingNotMutuallyPermutableSubgroups" Arg="[G, ]A, B" Comm="finds two subgroups which do not permute" />
<Description>
This function returns a pair of the form [ <A>A</A>, <A>V</A> ] with <A>V</A> a
subgroup of <A>B</A> or of the form [ <A>W</A>, <A>B</A> ] with <A>W</A> a subgroup of <A>A</A>
in which both subgroups do not permute, or <K>fail</K> if this pair does not
exist because the product is mutually permutable.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="AreTotallyPermutableSubgroups" Arg="[G, ]A, B" Comm="checks whether both subgroups are totally permutable" />
<Description>
This function returns <K>true</K> if the subgroups <M>A</M> and <M>B</M> of <M>G</M> are
totally permutable,
that is, every subgroup of <M>A</M> permutes with every subgroup of
<M>B</M>, and <K>false</K> otherwise. The method used here checks only that
every cyclic subgroup of
<M>A</M> permutes with every cyclic subgroup of <M>B</M>.
<P/>

The method with two arguments assume that <M>A</M> and <M>B</M> have a common
supergroup. 
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="OnePairShowingNotTotallyPermutableSubgroups" Arg="[G, ]A, B" Comm="finds two subgroups which do not permute" />
<Description>
This function returns a pair of the form [ <A>V</A>, <A>W</A> ], with <A>V</A> a
subgroup of <A>A</A> and <A>W</A> a subgroup of <A>B</A>, such that both subgroups do
not permute, or <K>fail</K> if this pair does not exist because the product
is totally permutable.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);
Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> a:=AlternatingGroup(4);
Alt( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> b:=Subgroup(g,[(1,2,3,4),(1,3)]);
Group([ (1,2,3,4), (1,3) ])
gap> AreMutuallyPermutableSubgroups(g,a,b);
true
gap> AreTotallyPermutableSubgroups(g,a,b);
false
gap> OnePairShowingNotTotallyPermutableSubgroups(g,a,b);
[ Group([ (2,3,4) ]), Group([ (1,2)(3,4) ]) ]
gap> c:=Subgroup(g,[(1,2,3)]);
Group([ (1,2,3) ])
gap> AreMutuallyPermutableSubgroups(g,a,c);
false
gap> OnePairShowingNotMutuallyPermutableSubgroups(g,a,c);
[ Group([ (2,3,4) ]), Group([ (1,2,3) ]) ]
gap> AreMutuallyPermutableSubgroups(a,c);
false
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(3);
Sym( [ 1 .. 3 ] )
gap> a:=AlternatingGroup(3);
Alt( [ 1 .. 3 ] )
gap> b:=Subgroup(g,[(1,2)]);
Group([ (1,2) ])
gap> AreTotallyPermutableSubgroups(g,a,b);
true
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="AreMutuallyFPermutableSubgroups" Arg="[G, ]A, B, fA, fB" Comm="checks whether both subgroups of G are mutually f-permutable" />
<Description>
This function returns <K>true</K> if the subgroups <A>A</A> and <A>B</A> are mutually
<A>f</A>-permutable, and <K>false</K> otherwise. Here <A>A</A> and <A>B</A> are subgroups
of <A>G</A> and <A>fA</A> and <A>fB</A> are, respectively, lists of
subgroups of <A>A</A> and <A>B</A>, respectively.
<P/>

In the version with four arguments, <M>A</M> and <M>B</M> are assumed to be
subgroups of a common supergroup.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="OnePairShowingNotMutuallyFPermutableSubgroups" Arg="[G, ]A, B, fA, fB" Comm="finds two f-subgroups which do not permute" />
<Description>
This function returns a pair of the form [ <A>A</A>, <A>V</A> ] with <A>V</A> a
subgroup in <A>fB</A> or <A>B</A>  or of the form [&nbsp;<A>W</A>, <A>B</A>&nbsp;] with <A>W</A> a
subgroup in <A>fA</A> or <A>A</A>
in which both subgroups do not permute, or <K>fail</K> if this pair does not
exist. Here <A>A</A> and <A>B</A> are
subgroups of <A>G</A> and <A>fA</A> and <A>fB</A> are lists of
subgroups of <A>A</A> and <A>B</A>, respectively.
<P/>
In the version with four arguments, <A>A</A> and <A>B</A> are assumed to be
subgroups of a common supergroup.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="AreTotallyFPermutableSubgroups" Arg="[G, ]A, B, fA, fB" Comm="checks whether two subgroups are totally f-permutable" />
<Description>

This function returns <K>true</K> if the subgroup <A>A</A> permutes
with all subgroups in the list <A>fB</A> and <A>B</A> permutes with
all subgroups in the list <A>fA</A>, and <K>false</K> otherwise. Here <A>A</A> and <A>B</A> are subgroups
of <A>G</A>, <A>fA</A> is a list of subgroups of <A>A</A> and <A>fB</A> is a list of subgroups of <A>B</A>.
<P/>

In the version with four arguments, <A>A</A> and <A>B</A> are assumed to be
subgroups of a common supergroup.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="OnePairShowingNotTotallyFPermutableSubgroups" Arg="[G, ]A, B, fA, fB" Comm="finds two f-subgroups which do not permute." />
<Description>
This function returns a pair of the form [ <A>U</A>, <A>V</A> ] with <A>U</A> a
subgroup in <A>fA</A> or <A>A</A> and <A>V</A> a
subgroup in <A>fB</A> or <A>B</A>
in which both subgroups do not permute, or <K>fail</K> if this pair does not
exist. Here <A>A</A> and <A>B</A> are
subgroups of <A>G</A>, <A>fA</A> is a list of subgroups of <A>A</A> and <A>fB</A> is a list of subgroups of <A>B</A>.
<P/>

In the version with two arguments, <A>A</A> and <A>B</A> are assumed to be
subgroups of a common supergroup.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);
Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> a:=AlternatingGroup(4);
Alt( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> b:=Subgroup(g,[(1,2,3,4),(1,3)]);
Group([ (1,2,3,4), (1,3) ])
gap> AreTotallyFPermutableSubgroups(g,a,b,
>      MaximalSubgroups(a),MaximalSubgroups(b));
false
gap> OnePairShowingNotTotallyFPermutableSubgroups(g,a,b,
>      MaximalSubgroups(a),MaximalSubgroups(b));
[ Group([ (1,2,3) ]), Group([ (2,4), (1,3)(2,4) ]) ]
gap> AreTotallyFPermutableSubgroups(g,a,b,DerivedSeries(a),DerivedSeries(b));
true
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>



</Section>
</Chapter>
<Chapter><Heading>Other Functions in the <Package>PERMUT</Package> Package</Heading>

In this chapter we define some miscellaneous functions which have
appeared in the context of permutability, or some functions which have
been used for some of the functions of the package. 
<Section><Heading>Functions</Heading>

<ManSection>
<Attr Name="AllSubnormalSubgroups" Arg="G" Comm="all subnormal subgroups of a group" />
<Description>

This function computes all subnormal subgroups of <A>G</A>. The method used
to obtain this list consists in beginning with the list of all normal
subgroups of <A>G</A> and by adding all normal subgroups of the subgroups
in the list until no new subnormal subgroups appear. This computes the
complete list of subgroups, not only a representative of each
conjugacy class as other functions do.
<P/> 

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);
Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> AllSubnormalSubgroups(g);
[ Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] ), Group([ (2,4,3), (1,4)(2,3), (1,3)(2,4) ]), Group([ (1,4)
  (2,3), (1,3)(2,4) ]), Group(()), Group([ (1,3)(2,4) ]), Group([ (1,2)
  (3,4) ]), Group([ (1,4)(2,3) ]) ]
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Attr Name="PrimesDividingSize" Arg="G" Comm="primes dividing the size of a group" />

<Description>
This attribute gives a list of primes dividing the size of the finite
group <A>G</A>, without repetitions. Its code has been borrowed from the
&GAP; manual.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);
Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> PrimesDividingSize(g);
[ 2, 3 ]
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Attr Name="SylowSubgroups" Arg="G" Comm="Sylow subgroups of a group" />

<Description>

This attribute returns a list composed by one Sylow subgroup for every
prime dividing the size of&nbsp;<A>G</A>. If <A>G</A> is soluble, then it returns a
Sylow system or Sylow basis of <A>G</A>  by means of the function
<Ref Attr="SylowSystem" BookName="Ref" /> (a set composed of a Sylow subgroup for each prime
dividing the order of <A>G</A> permuting in pairs).
<P/>
<Log>
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);
Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> SylowSubgroups(g);
[ Group([ (1,2), (3,4), (1,3)(2,4) ]), Group([ (1,2,3) ]) ]
gap> s5:=SymmetricGroup(5);
Sym( [ 1 .. 5 ] )
gap> SylowSubgroups(s5);
[ Group([ (1,2), (3,4), (1,3)(2,4) ]), Group([ (1,2,3) ]), Group([ (1,2,3,4,
   5) ]) ]
</Log>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Prop Name="IsSCGroup" Arg="G" Comm="checks whether the group has simple chief factors" />

<Description>
This property is <K>true</K> if <A>G</A> is an SC-group, and <K>false</K>
otherwise. A group <A>G</A> is an SC-group if all its chief factors are
simple. Note that a soluble group <A>G</A> is an SC-group if and only if
<A>G</A> is supersoluble. The method used to check this property uses the
chief series if its is available or the group is not soluble.
<P/>

Since the methods for insoluble groups might on the computation
of a chief series with the function <Ref Oper="ChiefSeries"
BookName="Ref" />, they might not be available if the group is not
given as a permutation group.
<P/>

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);
Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> IsSCGroup(g);
false
gap> g:=GL(2,5);
GL(2,5)
gap> IsSCGroup(g);
true
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Prop Name="IsSylowTowerGroup" Arg="G" Comm="checks whether the group has a Sylow tower of supersolvable type" />
<Description>

This property takes the value <K>true</K> if <M>G</M> has a Sylow tower of
supersoluble type, and <K>false</K> otherwise.
<P/>
<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);
Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> IsSylowTowerGroup(g);
false
gap> g:=SmallGroup(75,1);
<pc group of size 75 with 3 generators>
gap> IsSylowTowerGroup(g);
true
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="Permutizer" Arg="G, U" Comm="permutizer of a subgroup" />
<Func Name="Permutiser" Arg="G, U" Comm="permutiser of a subgroup" />
<Description>


The permutiser of a subgroup <A>U</A> of a group <A>G</A> is the subgroup generated by all cyclic
subgroups of <A>G</A> which permute with <A>U</A>. If <A>U</A> is
permutable in <A>G</A> (in particular, if <A>U</A> is normal in <A>G</A>), then its
permutizer coincides with&nbsp;<A>G</A>.
<P/>
<Example><![CDATA[
gap> g:=SymmetricGroup(4);
Sym( [ 1 .. 4 ] )
gap> Permutizer(g,Subgroup(g,[(1,2,3)]));
Group([ (1,2,3), (2,3) ])
gap> Size(last);
6
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Func Name="AllGeneratorsCyclicPGroup" Arg="g, p" Comm="all generators of a cyclic p-group" />
<Description>


This auxiliary function returns the list of all generators of the cyclic
<M>p</M>-group generated by the <M>p</M>-element <M>g</M>. Here
<M>p</M> is a prime number. Since this function is not intended to be
used in interactive mode, no check is done that the
argument is a <M>p</M>-element. 

<Example><![CDATA[
gap> AllGeneratorsCyclicPGroup((1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9),3);
[ (1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9), (1,3,5,7,9,2,4,6,8), (1,5,9,4,8,3,7,2,6),
  (1,6,2,7,3,8,4,9,5), (1,8,6,4,2,9,7,5,3), (1,9,8,7,6,5,4,3,2) ]
]]></Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

</Section>
</Chapter>
</Body>
<Bibliography Databases="biblio.xml" Style="alpha" />
<TheIndex />
</Book>
